[SPEAKER_01]: After having made the commitment to training in the eight precepts as recommended by the Buddha, I do see myself failing and making mistakes.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this happens, my mind gets at me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel remorse about my shortcomings and the only way out that I know of is to fall back into behavior that is against the precepts or against other values that I uphold.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shall I give in to what my mind suggests, loosen up the moral constraints I put myself under, or is there another way to resolve this internal struggle that is in line with the Buddha's teaching?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you feel remorse for what you did, then why would you randomly decide not to feel remorse for doing it again?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where... it is a common line of thinking, but if you examine it closely, you realize it doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you feel remorseful for doing something, then surely you would be... you would feel more remorseful for doing it more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just maintain the perception of shame in regard to that same action.
[SPEAKER_00]: And recognize that, well, it's gonna feel unpleasant that you failed, but if you actually stay in line and don't abandon the determination you... don't intentionally throw away the determination you initially made, you will automatically not want to do it more, because it feels shameful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I... let's say I gave in in the first place because I couldn't bear the unpleasantness of my mind pressuring me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so then still feel ashamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, feel ashamed that... so you failed the first time, you failed the second time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, feel even more ashamed of failing the third time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the problem is that you kind of... or people usually would feel like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want to feel the burden of feeling even more like a failure, so I just move the goalpost and then I give up on the goal to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, if you keep it, then the more you fail, the worse you will feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, at some point, it will have to happen that if you kept the goal and you were failing at it, the pain will get strong enough for you to, you know, at least determine not to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you might fail again, which is expected.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, what you're training yourself is not for the
[SPEAKER_00]: You're training yourself for the shame to be stronger than the pressure to act.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's essential that you don't move the goalpost and think that, like, well, it's only really... it only really counts when I have, like, a perfect stretch, where immediately upon deciding that I would abstain, I have successfully abstained.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are relevant reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the pressure didn't come up in the first place, because of circumstances, because of whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... the point of the faculty that you're training, is that your shame is stronger than the pressure for you to act unwholesomely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it should be proportional to the worse the misbehavior is, and the more persistent it is, the more ashamed you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... it's... you really can't, eh... force it or speed it up any more than that, because that's where you would go wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would think, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Essentially, you would do things still rooted in avoiding the discomfort, and that's what would fail to teach the mind the lesson of, I shouldn't do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you stay with that discomfort of that failure, then, well, even if you keep failing, at least it's sinking in that this is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, the the shame that accompanies acting out of unwholesome intentions will be more painful than the pain of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't abandon the reasoning, the faith and the reasons why you were trying to restrain yourself to begin with, then the more you fail, the clearer it becomes, or the clearer the failure becomes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start to see or make the connection of why you shouldn't have been doing this to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be good if it were, but you have to take into account that the failure will keep happening, but the growth comes not from the amount of times you didn't fail.
[SPEAKER_00]: The growth is the growth of the sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't take that out of the picture and then expect to still be making progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: Technically, not failing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the wrong order, where you think, like, it's worse to have a determination and to fail.
[SPEAKER_00]: Naturally, that feels bad, but the thing is that the measure is not how many times you fail in and of itself, it's how much of that sense of shame growing, perception of danger growing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if my... like if I fail, I make mistakes, and my mind keeps pressuring me into the directions of making basically the same mistakes again, it's a sign of... that it hasn't really understood, whereas when it would actually stay with that sense of shame more, it would be a sign that it actually gets the message more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, if the danger stands out over the benefit, then you won't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not going to happen if you just look away from the problem, look away from the fact that you still might give in by sort of, yeah, tweaking the circumstances or just doing things in order to avoid the failure as a goal in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to think more in terms of the failure is when I fail and I don't maintain the sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the much worse type of failure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, either... like, even if you don't fail, the... the... it's actually worse if you quote-unquote succeed, not doing certain actions externally, but you don't have a sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, if you do fail, and you give in, but you maintain a sense of shame, because letting go of the sense of shame, or you could call it the perception of danger, is delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And delusion is worse than greed or aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the worst of the three defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kurose, it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha said, eh... the worst of all blameworthy things is a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wrong view comes hand in hand with you having done something unwholesome, having done something against the precepts, and not experiencing it as an issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is the worst of all blameworthy things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Far worse than somebody who did the bad thing, but to the extent of its badness, feels remorseful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the shame and remorse are the first two or the second and third faculty of a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's as well why in the suttas, when people come to the Buddha and
[SPEAKER_01]: He would confess their shortcomings to him, and sometimes even pretty grave things.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would actually say to them that it's a progress, kind of, yeah, having the sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would say, like, well, not having transgressions is, in itself, growth in the noble one's discipline, because he also gave this simile where he... one ascetic that he met had this view that
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody doesn't do bad actions by body, speech and mind, then they are... they can be declared as a pure and accomplished ascetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they would have said, if that was the case, then a child, newborn child, that doesn't even have the ability to
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that just goes to show, again, that the sense of shame, similar to the Noble Eightfold Path, it's the view that certain things are unwholesome, that then leads to the right speech and the right
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the right action just done in and of itself in an isolated context, which could be accidental.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the combination of your perspective, that says this is unwholesome, together with the abstinence, that makes the abstinence wear away craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abstinence by itself, without the perception of non-abstinence as being unwholesome, without that avenue being closed, is just like a child.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be similar to just make... turning yourself... like an extreme version of that would be turning yourself into a vegetable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you wouldn't do anything bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... it's not... the doing... the non-doing of anything bad is not happening because you actually developed that perception of unwholesomeness.